Richard A. Rice papers CA.MS.00324
Smith College Archives
Richard A. Rice papers
1879-1955
Smith College Archives
Rice, Richard A.
CA.MS.00324
2.458 linear feet (6 containers)
Richard A. Rice was a professor of English at Smith College. His papers contain biographical material, correspondence, course materials, writings and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Richard Ashley Rice, an authority on Lord Byron and a professor of English at Smith College from 1916-1946, was born in Burlington, Vermont on January 29, 1878, to Richard Austin and Marion Rice. He received his B.A. from Williams College in 1899, his M.A. from Harvard in 1903, and went on to study at the Sorbonne in Paris in 1906. Rice taught at Lawrenceville School, the high school from which he also graduated in 1896, from 1899-1900, the United States Naval Academy from 1903-06, Harvard University from 1907-09, and Indiana University from 1909-16 before he came to Smith in 1916. Rice specialized in 18th and 19th century English literature and was considered an authority on Lord Byron. His publications include: A Book of Narratives, Tom Jones (abridged), Studies of Wordsworth and Byron, College and the Future, The Best of Byron, Robert Louis Stevenson, and Rousseau and the Poetry of Nature. He also contributed to a number of magazines, including The Atlantic, Harper's and Independent, and wrote a number of mystery novels, short stories and poems. Rice became Professor Emeritus at his retirement in 1946 and taught at Wesleyan University for a year as visiting professor. Rice married three times, first to Anna Mary Dye in 1916, then to Jean D. Macdonald in 1933, and lastly to Frona M. Brooks Huges in 1951. He died on August 6, 1955 at the Newton-Wellesley Hospital in Newton, Massachusetts. Rice was survived by Frona, class of 1922, a son, Richard Ashley Rice, Jr., a daughter, Marianne Rice Zagorski, and two stepdaughters, Octavia and Anne Hughes.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes biographical material, writings and photographs of Rice and of his family. The correspondence contains letters to Rice's parents, wives, children, and extended family as well as to his many friends including former students. There are fourteen letters written from Rice's first wife Anna Mary Dye to Rice and their children from Germany in 1934-36. His other correspondents include Vachel Lindsay, William Allan Neilson, A. Seelye Bixler and Mina Kirstein Curtiss. The first folder of professional correspondence contains employment letters from the various colleges at which Rice worked, as well as correspondence with doctors. The course materials include lecture notes, exams and reading lists for many of Rice's various literature courses, as well as student papers from various classes in the 1920s and 1930s.
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Richard A. Rice papers were donated to the College Archives by Rice's son, Richard A. Rice, Jr., and his daughter Marianne R. Zagorski.
Smith College--Faculty
- Biography, 1895-1955 (Box 1)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence - Family (Box 1)
- Rice, Richard Austin, 1889-1899 (Box 1)
- Rice, Richard Austin, 1900-24; undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Richard Austin & Marion, 1891-1916 (Box 1)
- Rice, Marion F., 1889-93 (Box 1)
- Rice, Marion F., 1894-99 (Box 1)
- Rice, Marion F., 1900-25 (Box 1)
- Rice, Marion F., undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Anna Mary Dye, 1919-22 (Box 1)
- Rice, Anna Mary Dye, 1923-29 (Box 1)
- Rice, Anna Mary Dye, 1934-36 (Box 1)
- Rice, Anna Mary Dye, undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Anna Mary Dye, undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Jean Macdonald, 1938; undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Richard A. Jr., 1928-29; undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Marianne, undated (Box 1)
- Rice, May, 1892-1916; undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Roser, 1892-1923; undated (Box 1)
- Rice, Roger May, 1894-99 (Box 1)
- "Aunt Lollie", 1899-1916; undated (Box 1)
- "Aunt May & Uncle Will", 1891-1928; undated (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous, 1879-1916; undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence - Friends (Box 2)
- A-B, 1907-28 (Box 2)
- C, 1897-1945 (Box 2)
- D-F, 1906-25 (Box 2)
- G, 1906-25 (Box 2)
- H, 1903-31 (Box 2)
- K-M, 1891-1921 (Box 2)
- N-R, 1907-45 (Box 2)
- S-W, 1891-1933 (Box 2)
- Ayres, Ann, 1926-28 (Box 2)
- Gassaut, Katherine, 1903-16 (Box 2)
- Hopkins, Charlotte, 1898-03; undated (Box 2)
- Hubbell, Juliette Emily, 1899-1900 (Box 2)
- Hubbell, Juliette Emily, 1901 (Box 2)
- Hubbell, Juliette Emily, 1902-16 (Box 2)
- Hubbell, Juliette Emily, undated (Box 2)
- Le favour, Henry, 1892-1916 (Box 2)
- Osborne, Lithgow, 1908-09 (Box 2)
- Perry, Lewis & Margaret, 1892-1928 (Box 2)
- Rutter, May, 1902-28 (Box 2)
- Todd, Charles F., 1921-29 (Box 2)
- Young, Karl & Frances, 1905-29 (Box 2)
- Unidentified, 1892-1949; undated (Box 2)
- Professional (Box 2)
- General, 1905-51 (Box 3)
- Publishers, 1904-28 (Box 3)
- Course Materials (Box 3)
- Backgrounds of Modern Literature, 1944-46 (Box 3)
- Browning, undated (Box 3)
- Eighteenth Century Literature - Exams, 1929-47; undated (Box 3)
- Eighteenth Century Literature - Reading Lists, undated (Box 3)
- Eighteenth Century Literature - Topics, 1942-46 (Box 3)
- George Eliot and Matthew Arnold, 1919-24; undated (Box 3)
- History of English Literature, 1918-25; undated (Box 3)
- Modern European History - Exams, 1919 (Box 3)
- Nineteenth Century Prose - Lectures, Exams, 1917-24 (Box 3)
- Nineteenth Century Prose and Reformers - Exams, 1925-44; undated (Box 3)
- Nineteenth Century Prose and Reformers - Reading Lists, 1941-44 (Box 3)
- Nineteenth Century Prose and Reformers - Topics, Lectures, undated (Box 3)
- Survey of English Literature before 1800 - Exams, 1933-42; undated (Box 3)
- Survey of English Literature before 1900 - Reading Lists, undated (Box 3)
- Survey of English Literature before 1800 - Topics, undated (Box 3)
- Types of English Prose Fiction - Exam, 1934 (Box 3)
- General Honors Exams; Comprehensive Exams, 1924-34; 1946 (Box 3)
- Reports on Honors Exams & Theses, 1926-38 (Box 3)
- Special Honors- 18th Century, 1926; 1935 (Box 3)
- Special Honors- 19th Century, 1924-38; undated (Box 3)
- Student Papers: A-H, 1920-40; undated (Box 3)
- Student Papers: I-W, 1929-35; undated (Box 4)
- Tutorial Bibliography, 1941 (Box 4)
- Writings (Box 4)
- Articles, Papers, 1892-1936 (Box 4)
- Fiction, undated (Box 4)
- Goethe, undated (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
- Notes, undated (Box 4)
- Poetry, undated (Box 4)
- Reviews by R.A.R.'s, 1918; 1937; undated (Box 4)
- Sampling, undated (Box 4)
- Themes, 1902-15; undated (Box 5)
- Thesis, undated (Box 5)
- Yearbooks, 1896; 1899 (Box 6)